<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>bash on Code - a programming blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.dnmfarrell.com/tags/bash/</link>
    <description>Recent content in bash on Code - a programming blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 09:03:41 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.dnmfarrell.com/tags/bash/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How to Split a String in POSIX Shell</title>
      <link>https://blog.dnmfarrell.com/post/how-to-split-a-string-in-posix-shell/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 09:03:41 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.dnmfarrell.com/post/how-to-split-a-string-in-posix-shell/</guid>
      <description>The POSIX Shell specification defines a minimalist shell language with few features compared to stalwarts like Bash. Yet POSIX shells are everywhere: Dash is the default on Ubuntu, and many Docker containers only have busybox ash. Minimalist shells use less resources and are faster than featureful shells like Bash and Zsh¹. They are more likely to be secure too, as the reduced feature sets are easier to reason about and provide a smaller attack surface for hackers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bash Function Names Can Be Almost Anything</title>
      <link>https://blog.dnmfarrell.com/post/bash-function-names-can-be-almost-anything/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jun 2021 20:19:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.dnmfarrell.com/post/bash-function-names-can-be-almost-anything/</guid>
      <description>A common misconception about Bash is that function names must follow the same rules that variables do. The Bash manual even suggests this:
 A word consisting solely of letters, numbers, and underscores, and beginning with a letter or underscore. Names are used as shell variable and function names. Also referred to as an identifier.
 In fact Bash function names can be almost any printable character. For instance I can define my own pre-increment unary function:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three Ways to Get a Unix Epoch in Bash</title>
      <link>https://blog.dnmfarrell.com/post/three-ways-to-get-a-unix-epoch-in-bash/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jun 2021 11:34:50 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.dnmfarrell.com/post/three-ways-to-get-a-unix-epoch-in-bash/</guid>
      <description>The Unix epoch time is the number of elapsed seconds since January 1st, 1970. Epoch times are handy because they&amp;rsquo;re not subject to timezone offsets, and they&amp;rsquo;re numbers, unlike ISO 8601 timestamps for example (&amp;ldquo;1970-01-01T00:00:00Z&amp;rdquo;). That makes them memory efficient, and more importantly, easy to do math with.
Here are three ways to get the epoch time in Bash.
Use Date You can use the date program to generate the epoch time by providing the %s formatting argument.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modulinos In Bash</title>
      <link>https://blog.dnmfarrell.com/post/modulinos-in-bash/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.dnmfarrell.com/post/modulinos-in-bash/</guid>
      <description>A modulino is a file which behaves like a library when it is imported, and like a script when executed. I first read about them in Mastering Perl, but you can create them in other languages too. Here&amp;rsquo;s how to do it in Bash.
Let&amp;rsquo;s say you have a simple script:
#!/bin/bash echo &amp;quot;Hello, World!&amp;quot;  A common refactor with scripts is to encapsulate all the code behavior in functions. As this script only does one thing, it&amp;rsquo;s a small change:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
